Well, the ECB and other central banks,
including maybe even the Fed, are very
likely to overreact to oil prices by
raising their benchmark policy rates,
that possibility is no longer so
straightforward. Even over there in
Europe, where policymakers as a group
tend to be more aggressively hawkish,
several of them have come forward
recently expressing serious and growing
concerns about the demand side of the
economy, especially where it comes to
jobs and workers. And to that effect,
fitting with that sentiment, two of the
world's leading energy agencies just
slashed their demand growth forecast in
a way we only see in periods like 2020
or 2009.
Worldwide, the initial indications,
especially where it comes to the labor
market, are already beginning to look
like the historic energy shock case. So
much so, even central banks are starting
to reassess what the real risk to the
economy truly might be. Now, they still
believe, by and large, it's about
inflation. However, we're getting more
and more indications on the other side.
And they were greatly aided by the
latest forecast from the US's Energy
Information Administration, which just
slashed its energy demand estimate to
basically zero for this year. And its
international counterpart, the
International Energy Agency, it went
even farther, saying it now believes
global energy demand will outright
shrink this year. Now, the last time
that happened was 2020, and before that
2009.
So, there is one critical factor in all
this that most people overlook or just
completely dismiss, including central
bankers and certainly at the stock
market. But that factor is really
beginning to be way too much to ignore.
That's the state of the global economy
before the shock even began, and that is
where the data and evidence is making a
huge difference right now already.
So, while everybody's talking about
inflation rate hikes from central
bankers, Steve, we've got a couple of,
you know, a whole bunch of data points
on Europe, but also oil demand that
suggests this really is moving toward to
the point that we you know even
officials are talking about but moving
toward the historical energy shock case.
Yeah, absolutely Jeff because you we go
back and let's take a look at Europe. I
mean there wasn't long ago that the
manufacturing sector was deep in
recession scenario territory. You know,
maybe even you know, financial crisis
level particularly in Germany it was
just like every month it got worse and
worse. Companies were laying off and
then the government steps in and says,
"Hey, we're going to do some you know,
military spending." And and everyone got
excited like, "Yes, this is what we
needed. It's going to turn around." Then
the oil shock hits and you get a lot of
front running of demand and we see that
here in the US state all of a sudden
factory renaissance and see everything's
going to be okay. It's booming but
there's this underlying problem. You
don't see hiring. And it's what you're
seeing is a pick up in hours in some
cases. You're seeing some optimism, you
know, some factories are saying, "Hey,
maybe this will get better." But they're
not reacting with the labor market. I
think this is a problem Europe's facing
right now is they've laid off so many
people. They know demand is going to
come down because you know, we talk
about inflation. And yes, is this going
to be inflationary? Of course. Are
prices going to go up around the world?
Yes, we're seeing it at the producer,
the intermediate, we're seeing it at the
consumer level. They're going to go
higher. But Jeff, we talk about the
right kind of inflation, demand led and
the wrong kind of inflation, energy led
and that's the problem here. Prices are
going to go up. Margins are going to get
squeezed. Consumers are going to pull
back. We see this replay time and time
again throughout history and we know
exactly what it means is companies are
going to have to lay off. They are
eventually going to cut hours. And as
you said, you start to sow the seeds of
it's pretty obvious where Europe's
economy is headed. You know, we've seen
this before. Four of the last five US
recessions, energy shocks. How Europe
comes out of this even remotely
unscathed, I have no idea. But it sure
looks to me exactly where they're headed
is yet another recession. And of course
we know the ECB is going to do what they
always probably do,
raise rates.
Raise rates right on into this recession
like they did in 2008 once and twice in
2011 just before that one started too.
It's It seems like a special talent. You
must have to sign up for it or you must
have to demonstrate the talent to raise
rates into recession in order to get a
top job at the ECB. It must be part of
the requirements uh job requirements.
But I think that's a good point, right
Steve? It's employment. Right, what
we're seeing is these uh increasingly
lots of negative employment indications
across Europe, which is I mean, that's
one thing that's going to get central
bankers' attention. What they're going
to say is, "Look, inflation, oil prices,
we equate those two things together.
Therefore, we need to hike rates." The
only thing that convinces them that
they're wrong is when unemployment
starts to rise. And when unemployment
rises even before you get to higher
energy costs,
then you got to say, "Oh boy, wait a
minute. The economy was supposed to be
picking up," as Steve said, "late 2024
the late 2025 into early 2026."
Everything was supposed to be already
turning around. Instead, we see in
European GDP, various employment numbers
for particular countries like I
mentioned France. France is a big one.
They've had negative payrolls for 2
years running. Unemployment rate is now
8.1% in France. Uh even across the
entire Euro area, employment has slowed
down to basically nothing. Uh the
year-over-year change in employment in
across the Euro area was half a percent,
which is well within recession
territory. So, if you're an honest ECB
official, you're sitting here thinking,
"Wait a minute. Uh employment the the
entire labor market across Europe, but
especially in the bigger economies like
Germany and France, already weak and
getting weaker before we get to the
energy shock. We know how the energy
shock plays out. We've seen it time and
again," as Steve mentioned, "energy
shock and recession, you use those two
things in the same sentence because they
usually go together." So, now all of a
sudden, the ECB is starting to think
starting to say, "Look, we've been
talking about hiking rates, but now we
have to maybe think about this a little
bit more than we thought we'd have to
think about it because we're already
getting indications in sentiment and
some hard data suggesting the recession
historical energy shock case is already
playing out across Europe. I almost
never do ads, and I say no to the vast
majority of those that are brought to my
attention, but I was thrilled to be able
to work with today's video sponsor,
Monetary Metals. And the reason is
because they're solving a big problem,
one that I've been highlighting for a
very long period of time. Gold is a safe
haven, but other than sitting in a
vault, it doesn't do anything. Monetary
Metals fixes that. They let you earn
real yield paid in physical gold without
giving up ownership. It's not a fund,
it's not a paper claim, it's your gold
working for you. Every month, more gold
gets deposited into your account. It's
simple, it's transparent, and it is
fully insured. If you believe in gold as
a long-term store of value as I do, this
changes everything. Go to
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
That's monetary-metals.com/snyder
for all the details. We absolutely thank
them for being the sponsor of today's
video, and now let's get back to it.
Yeah, Jeff, and you know, central banks
really did want to hike rates. And of
course, we know they really don't matter
too much, but the reality is, we've seen
this across the world. Everybody wanted
to bring rates up because they knew the
economy was weak. But if they could
bring them up, then they'd have an
excuse to bring them down to say, "Hey,
look, we can maybe fix things by
lowering rates." But the problem right
now is rates are still relatively low.
You can bring them back down to zero,
but the impact it's going to have on the
economy, which we already know is
nothing to begin with, but if we're a
central banker trying to convince the
world that this makes a difference,
they've got no margin for error. And
this is why you hear central bankers all
around the world when they speak, they
seem a bit nervous because this is going
to be one of those clear-cut times where
they're going to do what they always do,
cut rates, QE, or maybe they're going to
magically come up with something new
that they can do, and it's not going to
work. And the problem is their
credibility, which for you and I is
already pretty low, but for the rest of
the world remains relatively high, it's
going to be absolutely destroyed here.
Yeah, that's one thing you can do. You
can look at the marketplace. I mean, you
can look at you know, bond curves and
yield curves, but you can look at
forward interest rate markets, too, like
your EURIBOR futures, which are the euro
denominated twin to SOFR futures, which
I covered a little bit not not not that
long ago.
Um in SOFR futures, you have the frown
in the curve, which is the market
expectation that some central bankers,
including the Federal Reserve, might
actually be able to raise rates in the
near term, but eventually they're going
to have to turn around and lower them
again. That's the frown that the curve
shape has taken. There is a frown in the
EURIBOR futures curve, as well, which
says the same exact thing. It's not
exactly the same same shape, but it's
there's a frown there. And what it says
is that European central bankers are
very likely to raise rates in the near
term, but like everyone else around the
rest of the world, at some point, we
don't know when, they're going to turn
around and drop rates again. Now, the
the EURIBOR the term term EURIBOR curve
was already inverted before we got to
you know, at the end of February. So,
February 27th, before the ran conflict
showed up, the EURIBOR futures curve was
inverted, same as the SOFR futures
curve. Not as inverted as SOFR futures,
but it was inverted nonetheless, which
suggested before the energy shock even
began, like we're talking about here
with employment numbers that are just
coming in,
participants in the marketplace realized
the situation in the economy wasn't
good. And even though the ECB, and this
is great point that you made, Steve,
central bankers hate having low interest
rates, especially if they have low
interest rates facing economic weakness,
because they want to be able to bring
rates down from 5% to 1%. They want to
say, "Look, we we just we just cut rates
by 400 basis points. This is massive
stimulus." If you're already at 2%, and
you're facing economic weakness, what
they believe is that they don't have
enough altitude in their interest rates.
And so, what the market was saying
before we got to March was that they
didn't have nearly enough altitude and
they were facing substantial weakness
because the market was pricing rate cuts
by the ECB from 2% starting at 2%. Then
you get the energy shock and the market
says, well, they're going to probably
raise rates in the near term, but what
had what ends up happening afterward?
Well, you throw in the higher energy
costs, probably higher food costs, which
we're already starting to see, and a
whole bunch more of, you know, economic
difficulties, businesses laying off
workers, continuation in the
deterioration in employment that we've
seen already. Where are rates going to
end up going? They're not going to get
all that high to begin with before they
have to turn around. So you've got the
frown in the euro dollar futures curve,
which is the same as we've seen in the
silver futures curve, which is basically
central bankers are likely to raise
rates in the short run. However, they
realize that there is a danger to
employment and therefore the overall
economy. The real issue here, the real
question is, when do you see enough
weakness in the especially employment
that central bankers have to say, well,
maybe we can't hike rates. And what
we're already saying here by some of
these examples that we're getting is
that some of these central bankers,
especially in Europe, might already be
at least in that same discussion.
And you know, Jeff, that's almost a
surprise or thinking that cuz again, as
you said, historically the ECB's like,
oh, we'll just hike rates and then
whoops. But you know, let's talk about
the curve in the short term. Why is it
saying that rates are going to go
higher? It's because of inflation. And
we're seeing some signs that consumers
are absorbing it, but we know they can't
do that indefinitely. We know here in
the US, of course, there's tax refund
checks, they're drawing down savings,
but when we looked at the recent retail
sales report, where did we see the
issues were? Energy and food. So the
problem is for the average worker, for
the average household, but not just here
in the US, but all around the world, all
their money's going to food and energy.
And so what the curve is trying to say
here very clearly is, yes, in the short
term are central bankers likely with
some degree of probability to react to
high interest rates or higher inflation?
The answer is yes, because that's what
they do. But what the curve is trying to
say is, look, from an economic
perspective, what happens after that is
not because, you know, central bankers
raise rates and it does something. What
it's saying is, consumers are going to
get bogged down with inflation because,
you know, we talked about last week here
in the US, average hourly earnings went
negative due to inflation for the first
time in 4 years. So, as consumers spend
more money on food and energy, which we
can now uh virtually safely say there's
no signs that that's coming down in the
you know, intermediate future, that
means at some point they're going to
have to cut their discretionary
spending. As that back flows through the
economy, we're going to see, of course,
hours get cut, jobs lost. And that's
what the curve, that frown, is trying to
tell people is, hey, in the short term,
yes, can we get higher rates? If will
central bankers react to inflation? The
probability say they might, but after
that, it's the economic fundamentals of
growth and inflation are going to start
turning down, and the central bankers
are going to have to play catch-up here.
Yeah, that's their point is that when do
central because they have the ability
influence short-term rates, and wish
they didn't have that ability, but they
have that ability. So, what you're
really trying to figure out is at what
point do central bankers realize they
made a mistake on the inflation side?
Yes, there is consumer price rises in
the short run, but it doesn't lead to
what everybody imagines as inflation,
which is a sustained advance and
acceleration of broad prices, not just
gasoline. But they That's what this is
why they always use the term
second-order effects. So, gasoline costs
go up, and what they're worried about is
that gasoline costs go up, and then all
of these businesses in the economy that
see their input costs rise, then have to
adjust their prices, and then they then
other businesses have to adjust their
prices, and pretty soon, before you know
it, at least according to the theory,
inflation is broad-based and sustained.
It's deeply entrenched. Expectations get
unanchored and become something
different. That's what central bankers
are afraid of. They're afraid not
necessarily of oil prices rising, but
oil prices spilling over more broadly.
What we're saying and what the market is
saying is that's not how this works.
Because of the economy is not
experiencing, as Steve pointed out, it's
not a demand side increase. It's not
like incomes are rising and the job
market is robust, therefore higher
demand for all sorts of economic stuff
is bringing demand for oil up and
therefore there's more competition for
what oil there's available. That's not
what's going on. So, you have higher oil
prices for non-economic reasons like we
saw in 2022, and the only way the world
can respond to it is not by passing
further costs along to other customers
and other businesses, which those other
customers and other businesses can't
afford it. So, yes, you you can try to
pass higher energy costs along in places
where goods are a necessity, but at the
expense of basically everything else.
So, energy prices rise and maybe there's
a couple of second-order effects, but
the third-order effect is for demand to
fall everywhere else, and that's what
these ECB officials are already talking
about. Let me give you a couple of
quotes here. Uh first of all, you know,
Christine Lagarde at the last ECB
meeting said, "Directionally I know
where we're heading," which means she's
talking about we're going to hike rates,
and I think that's the base case. I
mean, Steve, you and I both expect that
the ECB's going to hike I mean, they
can't at this point they're they're
going to they're going to definitely do
it. Uh but however, we get some you
know, Vice President Guindos, I think
from Portugal, "The impact on growth
from the energy shock is going to become
much more visible over the coming
weeks." I noticed how and that's reason
I flagged this because he said coming
weeks, not months. He said the growth
impact, which means negative growth,
going to become much more visible over
the coming weeks. So, that's classic
energy shock case, but in the near term.
And even some mainstream economists are
starting to get cold feet on this, too.
This is the, you know, a senior
economist at Société Générale, "We're
already seeing some weakness in the
economy, and that will damp inflation
pressures and lower the risk of
second-round effects." And then he said
policy tightening, which he means rate
hikes, it's not really tightening, but
they call it that. Should thus not yet
be a done deal. So, I go back to the
beginning of this video, what I said
was, you know, we expect ECB to hike
rates. However, the possibility and the
probability is starting to diminish. And
the reason it's diminishing is because
we're seeing more visible weakness in
the economy, not, you know, straight-up
inflation leading into further inflation
and you know, the the the price spiral
that everybody imagines. We're getting
signs of economic weakness, the classic
energy shock case right now, and it's
only May. We're only a couple months
into this. That's not a good sign.
No, it isn't, Jeff. Now, I've gone back
and I've looked at, you know, some of
these prior energy cycles where we've
seen these spikes. And I kind of, you
know, looked and said, "How long do
prices have to stay up before we hit
some form of, you know, the point of no
return?" And in in a weakening, a
slowing economy, you're looking around 2
months. In a In a booming economy, it
can last longer. But, we're now past the
2-month mark. And I think that's kind of
what we're seeing from the ECB. Some of
the members are, you know, they're
getting uncertain and saying, "Look, we
were hoping that this was going to be a
transitory shock. It was going to come
down. And maybe that inflation was going
to push prices up, push producer prices,
maybe get people spending, which is kind
of what you want as people start
front-running demand. And then hopefully
that seeps through to the economy. You
get higher rate. And then next thing you
know, the thing kind of takes a life of
its own. Now, they're starting to
realize this problem isn't going away
anytime soon. The strait not likely to
reopen. And even if it did reopen
tomorrow, by the time oil flow started
really getting back out into the world,
it's still going to take a long time for
prices to come down. And the reality is
they're waking up to the fact that
consumers are can't afford it.
Businesses are have no choice, but they
can't pass it on. And the reality is, as
you said, they're going to hike rates,
and then immediately turn around and be
forced to cut them as the economy slams
face-first into a recession.
And that's what these oil, you know, oil
agencies and administration, you know,
the EIA and the IEA, that's what they
just said, too. They're basically saying
the same thing you did, Steve, which is,
"Look, we see where this is going, and
that's demand destruction." So, even if
regard Take the supply part of out of
the equation right now. What is it going
to look like on the demand side? And the
US Energy Information Administration
said, "We're looking at just 200,000
barrels a day growth for 2026," which is
absolutely anemic. You never see energy
growth at that limited level. Yeah, so
200,000 barrels a day down from 1.2
million. Now, 1.2 million wasn't great
to begin with. This is worldwide, not
just the United States. So, 1.2 million
growth, that was relatively weak and
concerning, which is one reason why we
were talking about a supply glut in the
oil market before we got to the energy
shock. So, down to 200,000 barrels a
day, which would be consistent with an
economy, a global economy, that's
experiencing a legitimate, full-blown,
synchronized recession. Now, the IEA
went even farther. They're forecasting
that they were forecasting for 2026 1.3
million barrels a day. So, million
barrels a day. So, similar to the EIA,
the IEA was thinking 2026 would be
relatively weak. But now they're
thinking it'll be minus 420,000 barrels
a day, which is something you only see
in some of the worst-cases for the
world. That would be, you know, 2020 is
a obvious one, but also 2008 and 2000
Really, 2009 more than 2008. So,
basically, globally synchronized
recession, that's kind of what these
agencies are forecasting for energy and
oil demand growth. What they're saying
is, regardless of supply, because prices
are so high, and because the economy is
not booming, and therefore can't really
absorb the energy shock and the energy
hit, we're looking at demand to really
fall off sharply, which is a huge red
flag because oil and energy overall,
these are really relatively price
inelastic goods, which means normally
demand doesn't fall off even when prices
rise precipitously. And because you have
to pay for oil in it Like you you said,
Steve, in the If the economy is
legitimately booming, oil prices go up,
you're not happy about it, it's painful,
it's not great, but you pay the cost and
you move on and you and you and the
economy can adjust. When the system is
weak, it can't. And so therefore, you
know, demand destruction shows up and
it's not just demand destruction of oil,
it's all the stuff that goes along with
it that's leading to lower demand for
oil.
Yeah, Jeff, and and you know, people I'm
talking to every day are seeing signs
that people are driving less. They're
cutting back on their vacation plans. Or
it's like, "Hey, we're already paid for
this year, so it's it's a it's a done
deal, but after that." But virtually
everybody I'm talking to and even
people, you know, that are high-income
earners saying, "You know what? I'm
starting to realize what's coming here
and I'm cutting back, too." And so
that's the challenge, that's the problem
where this thing starts to spiral to the
downside. Of course, we know exactly,
you know, the central bankers are going
to react, but as they always do, they're
going to make the wrong move, they're
going to raise rates and then turn
around and have to rapidly lower them.
The problem is this time, and again, we
look back at prior cycles. As you said,
they'd love to draw 400 basis points.
The problem is they don't have that room
to run, they don't have the tools, they
don't have anything to really stop this.
So yeah, what can we expect going
forward? At some point, we're going to
hit a breaking point. Central bankers
are going to cut, we're going to see a
fast path down to zero. The problem is,
just like raising rates isn't going to
control or or restrict the demand,
lowering rates isn't going to kick up a
huge amount of supply. It's not going to
be stimulative. And the problem is what
we're now facing is a very realistic
fact that the global economy is going to
hammer it hammered on this energy shock
and that it's going to be prolonged and
central bankers, once again, will have
absolutely no answer on how to fix it.
You're absolutely right, Steve. Another
point to watch as far as this point of
no return. Central bankers who right now
are all over oil prices are inflation
and rate hikes, once they suddenly pivot
to talking about jobs and rate cuts,
that's when you know, when they start
going back into the Pringles can,
you know it's already too late.
Which is why they're going to they're
probably going to hike rates more than
anybody else.
Cuz that's how it goes. It's what they
do.
>> [laughter]
>> It's what they do. Hey, it's a 2008
again. We should hike rates cuz that
worked out really well last time. People
forget 2011. They hiked rates twice in
2011 just before the recession started.
They're really good at this.